Declaration of Independence Collection
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Declaration of Independence Collection 1776-1942
MSS18135
60 items
1 containers plus 11 oversize
.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Miscellaneous copies of documents, mostly photostats, relating to the creation of the Declaration of Independence and its Virginia antecedents.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Stone, William James, 1798-1865.
Organizations
United States. Continental Congress.; United States. Declaration of Independence.; Virginia. Constitution (1776); Virginia. Declaration of Rights.
Places
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; Virginia--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Virginia--Politics and government--1775-1783.
Acquistion Information
The Declaration of Independence Collection consisting of miscellaneous copies of documents, mostly photostats, relating to the creation of the Declaration of Independence and its Virginia antecedents was obtained through various acquisitions and institutional sources, including the New York Public Library, University of Virginia Library, Massachusetts Historical Society, and the Department of State.
Access and Restrictions
The Declaration of Independence Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The Declaration of Independence Collection, dating from 1776 to 1942, consists of miscellaneous copies of documents, mostly photostats, relating to the creation of the Declaration of Independence and its Virginia antecedents. Originals are at the Library of Congress, New York Public Library, University of Virginia Library, Massachusetts Historical Society, and the Department of State. Also in the collection are nineteenth and early twentieth-century printed copies of the Declaration of Independence. Of note are photostats of the Virginia Constitution and Declaration of Rights, 1776; photostats of the Resolution for Independence passed by the Continental Congress on June 7, 1776; photostats of Thomas Jefferson's record of debates in the Continental Congress, July 1-12, 1776 (originals in the Thomas Jefferson papers at the Library of Congress); and two copies of William James Stone's facsimile edition of the Declaration of Independence, published for the U.S. Secretary of State in 1823, and one later edition of Stone's facsimile. It is possible that some of these documents were assembled for a 1943 exhibition at the Library of Congress, "Genesis of the Declaration of Independence."
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged largely in chronological order.
Container List
- "Ordinances Passed at a General Convention of Delegates and Representatives.. ." Williamsburg, May 6, 1776. Williamsburg: Alexander Purdie, 1776. Photostat. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Instructions Given by the Convention of Virginia to their Delegates, May 15, 1776." Photostat. Signed by John Tazewell and Edmund Pendleton. Original at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Virginia Declaration of Rights (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ms draft, copy, George Mason. Photostat. Original at Library of Virginia. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ms draft, copy, George Mason (not in Mason's hand). Photostat. Original in Emmet Collection, New York Public Library. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ms draft, George Mason and Thomas Ludwell Lee. Photostat. Original in George Mason Papers, Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "A Declaration of Rights," Virginia Gazette, June 1, 1776. Photostat. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “In Convention, June 12, 1776. A Declaration of Rights,” Virginia Gazette, Postscript, June 14, 1776. Photostat. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Thomas Jefferson, Virginia Constitution, Notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Constitution of Virginia, first ideas of Th. J. Communicated to a member of the Convention." Ms. Photostats. Original in Thomas Jefferson Papers, Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "A Bill for new modelling the form of government and for establishing the Fundamental principles of our future Constitution." Ms., incomplete. Photostats. Original in Thomas Jefferson Papers, Library of Congress. With transcript. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Continental Congress, Richard Henry Lee, Resolution for Independence, undated [June 7, 1776]. Ms. Photostat. Original in Continental Congress Papers, Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Continental Congress, Committee of the Whole, Resolution for Independence and the Appointment of a Committee to draft a Declaration of Independence, June 10, 1776. Photostat. Original at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William Fleming to Thomas Jefferson, Williamsburg, June 15, 1776. Photostat. Original at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Fleming to Thomas Jefferson, Williamsburg, June 22, 1776, with enclosure: "A plan laid before a committee appointed to prepare a form of government," annotated. Photostats. Originals at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Virginia Constitution, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - James Madison, comparison of the Virginia Constitution as adopted, June 29, 1776, undated Photostat. Original at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Constitution, adopted June 29, 1776, printed. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Jefferson, record of debates in the Continental Congress, July 1-12, 1776, written in 1825 for his autobiography. Photostats. Originals at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Continental Congress, Resolution for Independence, July 2, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Resolution for Independence, Committee of the Whole, July 2, 1776. Photostat. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Philadelphia Evening Post, July 2, 1776, first mention. Photostat. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Declaration of Independence, 1776. Miscellaneous photostats, facsimiles, printed copies (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thomas Jefferson, Rough Draft, [June 29, 1776]. Photostat. Original at Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Printed facsimile, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ms copy, July 4, 1776, Emmet Collection, New York Public Library. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ms copy, July 4, 1776, Washburn Collection, Massachusetts Historical Society. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dunlap copy, July 4, 1776, wafered into the Journal of the Continental Congress, 4 July 1776. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dunlap copy, July, 1776. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Facsimile pages of signatures of signers of the Declaration of Independence. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous Documents Relating to the Declaration of Independence, Copies (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter, Committee on Secrecy to John Ross, Sept. 27, 1776. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter, George Mason to Col. William Cabell, 6 May 1783, Emmet Collection, New York Public Library. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter, Thomas Jefferson to James Madison on debates, 1 June 1783. Library of Congress. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cabinet card photograph of stenographic copy of the Declaration of Independence, George Hawley, 1882. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "How the Declaration was Received in the Old Thirteen," in Harper's Magazine, July, 1892. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Genesis of the Declaration of Independence," typed item list of Library of Congress exhibit, February 12, 1931. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- John Binns edition (Box OV 1)
  - 4 Nov. 1818, autographed by John Q. Adams, James Porter, printer, 19 Apr. 1819. (Box OV 1)
  - Reproduced by Henry Sartain, 1876. (Box OV 1)
  - Reproduced by H. J. Toudy and A. J. Stone, published by H. J. Toudy Co., 1876. (Box OV 1)
- Holland Studio edition, autographed by John Hay, 8 Nov. 1902. (Box OV 2)
- James McBride issue, autographed by James G. Blaine, 18 Dec. 1891. (Box OV 3)
- Department of State issue, undated (Box OV 4)
- Department of Interior issue, undated (Box OV 4)
- National Archives issue, undated (Box OV 4)
- Bureau of Engraving and Printing issue, 1939. (Box OV 4)
- Ohman Co. reproductions of William J. Stone edition, 1942 (3 copies). (Box OV 4)
- P. F. Collier & Son Co. issue, 1934. (Box OV 5)
- C. A. Elliott issue, undated (Box OV 5)
- Ohman Co. issue, 1942. (Box OV 5)
- A. G. Gilney issue, 1883. (Box OV 5)
- Leggo Bros. & Co. issue, 1876. (Box OV 5)
- James D. McBride issue, 1874, with local advertisements (2 copies). (Box OV 5)
- Thomas Morrison, 1832, with advertisements. (Box OV 5)
- H. Phelps, 1834(?), with advertisements. (Box OV 5)
- B. D. Rising Paper Co., undated (Box OV 5)
- G. R. Russell issue, 1856. (Box OV 5)
- Swander & Bishop Co. issue 1865. (Box OV 5)
- Tanner, Valance, Kearney & Co., undated (Box OV 5)
- West Publishing Co. issue, 1920(?). (Box OV 5)
- William Woodruff issue, published by O. Rogers, with photocopy, undated (Box OV 5)
- American Bank Note Co. issue, 1876. (Box OV 5)
- Unknown (2 items), undated (Box OV 6)
- National Liberty Insurance Co. issue, undated (Box OV 6)
- New York Times issue, 4 July 1897. (Box OV 6)
- Applebaugh-Jones Co. issue, undated (Box OV 6)
- John Hancock Insurance Co. issue, undated (Box OV 6)
- Norris Peters issue, 1873. (Box OV 6)
- Daughters of the American Revolution issue, undated (Box OV 6)
- Photograph of the Department of State copy, undated (Box OV 6)
- Unidentified issue of Jefferson's draft of the Declaration of Independence, undated (Box OV 7)
- Centennial Offering Co. issue, reproduction by Schaefer, Waeschle and Kohner, 1876. (Box OV 7)
- Baltimore Sun issue, 4 July 1887. (Box OV 7)
- A. F. Jayne issue, 1869. (Box OV 7)
- Ensign, Brielman and Fanning issue, 1860. (Box OV 7)
- Photographs by L. C. Handy (3), 1903. (Box OV 7)
- Photograph by Library of Congress, with 4 photographs of signatures, 1941. (Box OV 7)
- Baldwin & Gleason engraved miniature, undated (Box OV 7)
- Reproduced by Norman H. Chance, 1923. (Box OV 8)
- Benjamin Owen Tyler edition, autographed by Richard Rush, engraved by Peter Maverick, 10 Sept. 1818. (Box OV 8)
- William J. Stone facsimiles, engraved for the Department of State by order of J. Q. Adams, secretary of state, July 4, 1823. (Box OV 9)
  - Copy 1 (Box OV 9)
  - Copy 2 (Box OV 10)
  - Copy 3, from the later edition struck from the same plate with the legend, lower left: "W.J..Stone SC, Washn." (Box OV 11)